Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Okay.
Let's just do this. Today's דף daf is קז. Kaf Zayin. We
pick up on the משנה Mishna on the bottom of קו עמוד
ב. Kaf Vav Amud Bet. We're in the middle of talking about
צידה, tzedah, capturing. So let's get started. Says the following: ישב אחד
על הפתח, Yoshav echad al hapetach, if one person stands by a
door. This is going on the case of the previous משנה Mishna
that a deer entered into a house. So you didn't exactly lock
the door, which was discussed at the tiny little משנה Mishna yesterday,
which got into the whole issue about שנים שעשוהו, Shnayim she'asuhu, but
one person sat by the door, and this also continues that in
some way, ולא מילאהו, velo mil'uhu, he did not fill the door.
ישב השני ומילאהו, Yoshav hasheni umile'uhu, and the second person sat next
to him and the two of them blocked the door, blocked the
opening, I should say.
השני חייב, Hasheni chayav, the second one is חייב. chayav. Now this
is in contrast to the case of שנים שעשוהו Shnayim she'asuhu before,
because there they did it at the same time, and there there
was the debate of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon whether or not זה יכול וזה לא יכול, zeh yachol
vezeh lo yachol, they're both חייב chayav or not. Here though, they
did it sequentially. So after the first one sat down, then the
situation was the first one had done nothing and the door was
half full. So then it was the second one who did the
entirety of the act of closing a partially open doorway and therefore
it is all the second one's obligation. So that's השני חייב. hasheni
chayav.
ישב הראשון על הפתח ומילאהו, Yoshav harishon al hapetach umilehu, now the
first one sat by the door and filled it. ובא שני וישב
בצדו, Uba sheni veyashav betzido, the second one came and sat down
next to him, or it would probably make more sense to say
that he like in front of him or something behind like as
we'll see. אף על פי שעמד הראשון והלך לו, Af al pi
she'amad harishon vehalach lo, even though the first one got up and
left, הראשון חייב, harishon chayav, the first one is חייב chayav because
he sat down and filled it all by himself, and when the
second one sat down next to him, the door was already blocked.
והשני פטור, vehasheni patur, the second one is exempt even after the
first one leaves, because now the first one leaves, the second one
is continuing to block the door.
But when he actually did his act of sitting down, he did
nothing new. He did not block the door. So it's not like
we say that by continuing to sit now, you are continuing to
block the door and the act of continuing to sit is capturing
the deer. The deer was already captured when you sat down, so
you are not actually now capturing the deer again, you're just static.
הא למה
זה דומה, Ha lema zeh domeh, you know, what is this similar
to?
לנועל את ביתו לשמרו ונמצא צבי שמור בתוכו. Lenoel et beito leshomro
venimtzah tzvi shamur betocho. Somebody who came to lock his house to
watch his house, like he was leaving, he was walking out of
his house and he locked the door, and then he discovered that
a deer was in his house. You don't have to say, oh
my god, so I accidentally locked a deer in my house, I
better unlock the door and let it go free. It's already locked.
What you did was nothing wrong, you were מתעסק, mit'asek, you were
totally unaware that you were locking it, that a deer was in
your house when you locked it. And now that it happens to
be that a deer is captured in your house, you don't have
to reverse the situation. You're no longer doing the act of capturing.
You know, a lot as opposed to like a lot of people
think, right, you accidentally walk into a room, you're not thinking, you
turn on a light, oh my god, and then you've got to
turn off the light, which is also. So here, luckily there's no
מלאכה melacha of freeing a captured animal, so that's not a concern,
but nevertheless, it is saying that leaving the static situation as it
is is not a problem if in your original act you did
nothing. Now it is an interesting question about what if, you know,
that act continues some let's say meaning not, you know, some type
of like active not action but let's say like pressure. For example,
I'm imagining let's say, you know, let's give an example. Well, for
example, for the light example I'm thinking, let's say you pushed a
button and by continuing to hold the button the light was on.
And you pushed a button without thinking and you realize that it's
שבת. Shabbos. So now, you know, it actually requires although you're not
moving your finger it actually requires ongoing pressure, right? If it's not
like completely static like sitting, right, you've got ongoing pressure to keep
that button pressed. Is that what?
That's called a dead man's switch.
Dead man's switch. Is that considered to be, you know, continue to
do the מלאכה? melacha? Let's say for example in this deer case,
you went ahead and you had a door that was a little
bit like collapsing. So you closed the door, you didn't realize there
was a deer in it, but you were like holding it up
like, you know, so it wouldn't fall down. You're actually applying pressure
to it so it wouldn't fall down. And then you realize there
was a deer in it. Would the continuing of applying pressure be
considered to continue to do the מלאכה? melacha? That's, I don't know,
I'm just putting that out there. It's a little bit different than
the case here where you're just סתם stam sitting. Okay, so but
certainly in the case where you're סתם stam sitting to, you don't
have to reverse the situation. Okay, so let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב. Amar Rabbi
Abba amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav. So said רבי Rabbi
אבא Abba in the name of רבי Rabbi חייא בר אשי Chiya
bar Ashi in the name of רב. Rav. נכנסה ציפור תחת כנפיו.
Nichnesa tzippur tachat knafav. If a bird flew into, flew under your,
let's say, cloak, your toga, your raincoat, or something, יושב ומשמרו עד
שתחשך. yeshev u'mishamro ad shetecheshach. You can sit and watch it until
it gets dark. You don't have to like open up your raincoat
and let it fly away, which seems pretty clear. It seems to
be exactly the case in the משנה, mishna, although the language of
יושב ומשמרו yeshev u'mishamro again, sort of makes you wonder like, are
you not just not freeing it, but are you also somehow doing
something that's enabling it to remain caught? And is that like allowed,
now that it's currently caught? Let's say it's currently caught underneath my
cloak, and what I do is I walk into my house and
I lock the door in my house. Okay, so at the act
of locking the door in my house, I wasn't capturing it more,
but now I can take off my cloak and it'll still be
caught captured in my house, right? So is that okay because at
that moment I was not doing anything that actually was capturing an
uncaptured animal. And a little bit you get that language that that
might actually be okay. Goes back to my idea of continuing to
hold up the door. Maybe even if I do require ongoing pressure,
that I'm allowed to do that because it's already captured. Let's say
for example, let's go back to the משנה mishna case and say
I'm sitting in front of the front of the house, the deer
is in it. I did or didn't do a מלאכה, melacha, I
decided to sit here, you know, when שבת Shabbos began or before
שבת, Shabbos, that's irrelevant. And I say to Mike, I say Mike,
I need a bathroom break. Come here, come sit next to me
so I can go off and get go do a bathroom break.
So Michael knows the reason he's coming to sit next to me
is so that the deer will remain caught. But when he actually
sits down, he's sitting down, he is filling up a door of
a captured deer. So he is not actually capturing an uncaptured animal,
right? So maybe that is okay. And maybe my example about holding
up the pressure against the door that's falling, that's okay, because even
though you're continuing to exert pressure, you are but you are you
know you're you're not capturing an uncaptured animal until the door actually
falls down. The animal is still captured, so you're still doing an
act, but the act is to a captured animal. And you do
get a little bit of the sense that the גמרא Gemara is
moving in that direction.
Yes, you're right.
It's human nature to make a more conscious effort if it's there.
Right, and that might be.
It's more conscious of how humans, how, you
know, that's true and it might be assuming that, it might be
assuming that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Right, so the
גמרא Gemara continues. מתיב רב נחמן בר יצחק. Maysiv Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak. So רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak asks this.
יושב הראשון על הפתח ומילאוהו בא שני ויושב בצדו. Yoshev harishon al
hapetach umil’uhu ba sheini veyoshev betziddo. So one guy filled it and
the second guy came and sat next to him. אף על פי
שנסתלק הראשון והלך לו, Af al pi shensistalek harishon vehalach lo, the
first guy left and left, הראשון חייב והשני פטור. harishon chayav vehasheini
patur. The second one is exempt. מאי לאו פטור אבל אסור? Mai
lav patur aval assur? It sounds like the second one is exempt
but it's still forbidden for the second one to have acted that
way. And maybe specifically because you're trying to keep it captured, you
know, so doesn't it sound like the second one is actually should
not be doing it לכתחילה? lechatchila?
So the גמרא Gemara says לא פטור מותר. Lo patur muttar.
No, we don't mean exempt and forbidden, we actually mean exempt and
it's permissible. We said exempt because we're contrasting it to the first
one who's חייב, chayav, but really it's permissible for the second guy
to do it. הכי נמי מסתברא. Hachi nami mistabra. That makes sense.
מדתני סיפא. Middetanei seifa. What is this similar to? למה זה דומה
לנועל ביתו לשומרו ונמצא צבי שמור בתוכו. Lemah zeh domeh leno’el beito
leshomro venimtza tzvi shamur betocho. Somebody who closes his house to lock
his house without realizing there's a deer and
there happens to be a deer in it. מכלל דפטור מותר. Mikh’lal
depatur muttar. In that case, you can't say that it is פטור
אבל אסור patur aval assur because the guy thinks there's nothing in
his house. So a guy locking his house, of course it's מותר,
muttar, right? So there where it says in that case, מכלל דפטור
מותר, mikh’lal depatur muttar, it means not only exempt, it means it's
מותר muttar because that other case there's nothing you could tell the
guy, of course it's מותר. muttar. שמע מינה. Shema mina. That is
a good point. So the גמרא Gemara says איכא דאמרי. Ika d’amri.
Some say that we started in the other way. אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak af
anan nami tanina. אף על פי שנסתלק הראשון והלך לו הראשון חייב
והשני פטור. Af al pi shensistalek harishon vehalach lo harishon chayav vehasheini
patur. Rather than starting by challenging the statement that you're allowed to
guard you know that bird that's caught in your cloak, he said
no, actually that's exactly like our משנה. mishna. משנה Mishna says the
second guy is exempt. מאי לאו פטור מותר? Mai lav patur muttar?
And presumably it means not just exempt but it means exempt and
permissible. So it's exactly our משנה. mishna. גמרא Gemara says לא פטור
אבל אסור. Lo patur aval assur. Maybe the משנה mishna means that
it's exempt but forbidden. הא מדתני סיפא. Ha middetanei seifa. You can't
say that. Since the end says למה זה דומה לנועל ביתו לשומרו
Lemah zeh domeh leno’el beito leshomro ונמצא צבי שמור בתוכו. venimtza tzvi
shamur betocho.
It's similar to the guy who went to lock his house and
it happened to find oh my god there's a deer there that
we say מכלל דפטור מותר. Mikh’lal depatur muttar. So that case is
obviously a case of מותר. muttar. The guy is oblivious. He thinks
that there's nothing there. So it's a מתעסק mitaseh case. So in
that case clearly he's allowed to lock his house if he thinks
there's nothing there. So you see when we say פטור patur we
really mean not just exempt but we mean מותר. muttar. שמע מינה.
Shema mina. The גמרא Gemara says that is actually a good example.
Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. Says שמואל. Shmuel.
Now because we mentioned this idea of פטור patur as a פטור
מותר, patur muttar, פטור אבל אסור, patur aval assur, we mention the
issue, we look at that general use of the word פטור. patur.
bringing us way back a hundred דפים Dapim to the very beginning
of the מסכת Masechet where we quoted this famous statement of שמואל.
Shmuel. Let's take a look. אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel said שמואל Shmuel
כל פטורי דשבת פטור אבל אסור. Kol paturei d'Shabbat patur aval asur.
Every time it says exempt on Shabbat, exempt means okay, you didn't
violate a biblical prohibition, you're exempt from a קרבן, Korban, but it
still is rabbinically forbidden. פטור Patur generally means פטור אבל אסור. Patur
aval asur. לבר מהני תלת Levar mehani telat דפטור ומותר, de'patur u'mutar,
there are three cases where it says פטור Patur where it really
means it imprecisely. It really means that it's מותר לכתחילה. Mutar lechatchila.
חדא האי, Chada hai, one is the case here about the deer.
וממאי דפטור ומותר U'mimay de'patur u'mutar and how do you know it
means that it's permissible לכתחילה? Lechatchila? דתני סיפא, Detani seifa, the end
says למה זה דומה לנעול את ביתו לשומרו ונמצא צבי שמור בתוכו.
Lema zeh domeh lenoel et beito l'shomro v'nimtza tzvi shamur b'tocho.
It compares it to the guy who locks his house in his
oblivion. So obviously in that case it's מותר, Mutar, so here too
when it says פטור Patur it means מותר. Mutar. Okay, that's one
case. והאידך, Ve'haidach, what's case number two? המפיס מורסא בשבת, Hamapis mursa
b'Shabbat, somebody who squeezes out a like an abscess you know on
Shabbat להוציא ממנה לחה lehotzi mimena leicha and if so what? What?
אם לעשות לה פה. im la'asot lah peh. Right. אם לעשות לה
פה,
Im
la'asot lah
peh,
if you're doing it so you've got this thing that's filled with
pus on your on your somewhere on your body and you squeeze
it out. So if you do it to make an opening and
that the opening should like there should be a hole and it
should stay that way and somehow that'll help the thing heal, then
חייב. Chayav. Then you're חייב. Chayav. Now exactly what מלאכה Melacha it
is is unclear. רש"י Rashi says maybe it's a type of a
בונה Boneh or מכה בפטיש. Makeh b'patish. But somehow you're seen as
changing something about the person and making them better. It's very funny
why you'd be חייב Chayav under any circumstance. Maybe specifically there's an
idea of making a hole. Remember we talked about a hole, a
hole in a chicken coop. Yeah, doing בונה Boneh on a person
is a pretty funny idea. מכה בפטיש Makeh b'patish on a person
is also a funny idea. I know, so it's very hard to
understand exactly what that is. But for somehow if you make, maybe
because of בונה Boneh specifically one aspect of בונה Boneh is making
a hole, you remember like the hole in the chicken coop or
something. Holes made in things in order to make the air come
in and out is considered to be a type of a בונה.
Boneh.
Anyway, it's it's all hard to understand exactly what type of מלאכה
Melacha that is, but the more important thing for us is אם
להוציא ממנה לחה, im lehotzi mimena leicha, if the hole is being
made incidentally and you're just trying to get the pus out, then
פטור. Patur. Then you're exempt because getting pus out isn't a מלאכה
Melacha and the hole is incidental. Now that really becomes a type
of a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. Melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa. You know
the hole will be made, but you're not doing it for the
sake of the hole, you're doing it just to get the to
get the pus out. Okay, that's by the way an example of
that is a lot about opening packages is you know
if you open a package in order to make a like a
usable package, that's one thing. But if it's the only way to
get access to the stuff inside, then it's you know then it's
not really making the package, you're just getting rid of the covering
so you can get to the inside. So the most obvious case
for example that's מותר Mutar is you take a bag, I don't
know, let's say potato chips and you tear it in the middle.
You know, so it's completely unusable, you're basically just destroying the thing
and you're just doing it to get to the stuff inside. You
know, but what happens if you go ahead and you know you
make a like, now
not everybody says this is a problem because it's pre-made this way
and it's disposable, but think about what happens when you make a
hole in those milk cartons. Not the not the screw tops, the
milk cartons. You're actually creating something that's now a functional spout. Now
some people say it was already that way and it was folded
in and it was a seal and it was disposable. But anyway,
that's a case where it's more obviously problematic, right? So then there
are cases in the middle. Let's say I open the bag of
potato chips at the top at the opening. Am I doing it
so it's a usable bag or am I just using it because
it's a more convenient way to get to the stuff on the
inside? Okay, so that's similar in this issue of yes you're making
a hole, but your goal isn't to make the hole, your goal
is just to get the stuff out. So that's okay, that's a
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. Melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa. Now right right according
to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but that's this teaching because what שמואל
Shmuel is doing is he's talking when they say פטור Patur in
the משנה. Mishna. תוספות Tosafot by the way points out that there's
multiple times we say פטור Patur in ברייתות Beraitot where we mean
מותר, Mutar, but שמואל Shmuel is saying three times we say פטור
Patur in a משנה Mishna where it means מותר. Mutar. So this
משנה Mishna it means מותר. Mutar. Now how do we know it
means מותר? Mutar? Normally you're not לכתחילה lechatchila allowed to do a
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. Melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa. So he says
וממאי דפטור ומותר? u'mimay de'patur u'mutar? How do you know לכתחילה lechatchila
you're allowed to do it? דתנן Detnan we taught in another משנה
Mishna מחט של יד Machat shel yad ליטול בה
את הקוץ, litol bah et hakotz, you can, to take a normal
sewing needle if you're using it to remove a splinter, you know
that you know that's okay because it's not מוקצה Muktzah because you're
using it for a legitimate purpose. So basically implied in that is
לכתחילה lechatchila you're allowed to take a needle to remove a splinter,
even though in the act of removing a splinter you might make
a hole, you might, some blood might come out. And therefore again
that shows you that even though normally that should be a מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה Melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa and at least אסור דרבנן,
asur d'rabbanan, since we are saying you're allowed to take it for
that purpose we are indicating that it לכתחילה lechatchila is מותר. Mutar.
Now why is it לכתחילה. lechatchila. To מותר *muttar*, and that becomes
a very important principle of מצטער *mitzta'er*, that somebody that is suffering
in pain, discomfort, and so on, you’re allowed to do an איסור
דרבנן *issur d'rabbanan* for them on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. As I have
kept keep on telling you, there’s a lot of discussions about when
do you how much suffering and when do you need a דאבל
דרבנן *double d'rabbanan* and when is a סינגל דרבנן *single d'rabbanan* enough?
But the general principle here is yes, it’s מלאכה melacha. שאינה צריכה
לגופה *melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa*, but it is allowed even לכתחילה *lechatchila*
because it is done to alleviate pain and suffering.
Larry says, whereabouts does כסא דהרסנא *casa d'harsena* then? why would we
say you’re only Okay,
because that is only for for what’s called מיחוש בעלמא *michush b'alma*,
like a trivial little annoyance. When it gets to be worse, things
are allowed.
I guess it depends on
if a bad headache?
Yeah, yeah, yes, and that is an issue. Okay, ואידך *v'idach*, the
third case is הצד נחש בשבת *hatzad nachash b'Shabbat*, and this is
actually what we’re coming up to ממש *mamash* in the next משנה
Mishnah. *Mishna*. Somebody who traps a snake on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*, אם
מתעסק בו שלא ישכנו *im mitasek bo shelo yishachenu*, if you are
מתעסק *mitasek*, which is an interesting phrase here, you normally mean it’s
completely incidental, but here it means something like that. You’re really not
trying to capture it. Your complete focus is to get it to
not bite you. Okay, so the best way to get it to
not bite you, first maybe you try to ward it off with
a stick and then you say, go get something to put over.
Okay, so you’re not focused on capturing it. Your goal is to
stop it from biting you. פטור patur *patur*, you’re exempt, because then
you are it’s basically another מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melacha she'eina tzricha
l'gufa*. You’re capturing it, but not for the purpose of capturing it.
The purpose of capturing is you want the thing you captured. Here
it’s just to prevent it from biting you. So that is again
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa* and you’re exempt. אם
לרפואה חייב chayav *im l'refuah chayav*, but if it’s for healing, like
you want to actually capture the snake to take the venom out
or something, then you’re חייב chayav? *chayav*. וממאי דפטור מותר *u'mimai d'patur
muttar*? How do you know you’re allowed to לכתחילה *lechatchila* do it?
Maybe it’s only like a normal מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melacha she'eina
tzricha l'gufa*. דתנן ditnan, *detnan*, the other משנה Mishna. *Mishna*, כופין קערה
על הנר בשביל שלא תאחוז בקורה *kofin k'ara al haner bishvil shelo
te'echoz bakora*. You can put a vessel over a candle not to
extinguish the candle, but to prevent it from the flame catching on
the beams and starting a fire. ועל צואה של קטן *v'al tzoa
shel katan*, and you can put it over, let's say poop of
an infant. ועל עקרב *v'al akrav*, and on a scorpion, שלא תשך
*shelo tishach*, that it should not bite you. So the third case
is what’s relevant. You’re essentially capturing an animal, but if you’re capturing
an animal for the sake that it does not bite you, you
are allowed and it’s assuming that we’re not talking even less than
a סכנת נפשות *sakanat nefashot*. So to prevent yourself from such a
thing, it’s a little different than the other case. The other case
was to alleviate suffering, this is to prevent yourself from having suffering,
which is about to happen then and again obviously non-trivial suffering, then
it is מותר *muttar* even לכתחילה *lechatchila*. Okay, so הדרנא לך ההורג
*hadran lach hachoreig*, that ends the of this case of צידה *tzeida*.
Now we actually turn, although the next משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* interestingly again,
it’s so funny where the breaks are in this thing, continues a
discussion of צידה *tzeida* and also turns to a discussion of חבלה
chavala *chavalah*, yes.
So like let’s say there’s a roach in your apartment, you put
a cup over it, is that like צואה של קטן *tzoa shel
katan* or?
What are you afraid of of the roach?
Why would you want You just don’t like them. You don’t want
them running around in your apartment and you want to like kill
it after שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*.
Yeah, but that’s Okay, so it certainly would not be חייב chayav.
*chayav*, but the question is would it be enough to be מותר
*muttar*? Yeah, it’s hard to me to understand why. I mean another
type of thing, often often what you can do in that case
is if you get it to go on a piece of paper
and then you flush it down the toilet. So putting in water
won’t kill it. It certainly won’t kill it immediately or something like
that.
But anyway, different might be a mosquito.
Yeah, a mosquito is actually a danger. Yeah, mosquito definitely.
So you actually can’t kill a bee?
Definitely you could.
So you actually can’t put the cup on the roach?
I don’t think just having a roach running around is enough of
a צרה *tzara* to capture it. But it ruins שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*.
Alright, if it is, if you’re the type of person that’s extremely
איסטניס *istenis* and whatever and you’re seeing it all around, then maybe.
But these are questions. Look, these are the I tell you like
half of פוסק’ן *poskening* for שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is the what is
the degree of מצטער *mitzta'er* and like figuring out if you need
a סינגל דרבנן *single d'rabbanan*, דאבל דרבנן *double d'rabbanan* and how to
get something to be a סינגל *single* or a דאבל דרבנן *double
d'rabbanan*. That’s like all that's like 50 percent of פסק *psak* cases
on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*. Okay, exactly. Alright, so moving on. שמונה שרצים
Shmoneh Sheratzim האמורים בתורה *shmoneh sheratzim ha'amurim baTorah*, the eight
sort of not bugs, but rodents in the תורה Torah, *Torah*. The
תורה Torah *Torah* lists creeping animals. Give me the thing there. Can
you give me the חומש *Chumash*, the תנ"ך *Tanakh* over there? Okay.
The תורה Torah *Torah* says that there are eight eight rodents that
cause טומאה tumah. *tumah*. And they’re and the what do you call
it? And those things are understood to be unique even for הלכות
halachos, שבת Shabbos. *Hilchos Shabbat*. I’ll tell you why in a minute,
but let me read to you what they are. וזה לכם הטמא
בשרץ השורץ על הארץ *v'zeh lachem hatameh basheretz hashoretz al ha'aretz*. These
are the things that are טמא tamei *tameh*. החולד והעכבר והצב למינהו
*hacholed v'ha'achbar v'hatzav l'minehu*. So of course the wonderful Artscroll here does
not translate them, but let’s see if it... Okay, חולד *choled* is
generally a weasel or a mole,
or some say that it's a mouse and a frog. Okay, so
the first three are generally seen like weasel, mole, weasel, mouse, frog.
Those are the first three. Okay, those are not the... then there's
going to be a separate list here. והאנקה והכח והלטאה והחמט והתנשמת
*Veha'anakah vehakoach vehaleta'ah vehachomet vehatinshemet*. So what are these other ones? So
here it says hedgehog, viper, lizard, snail, a type of a...
some say this other one is a mole. Anyway, so five other
ones. אלה הטמאים לכם בכל השרץ eleh hatmei'im lachem b'chol hasharetz. *Ele
hatme'im lachem bechol hasheretz*. כל הנגע בהם במותם יטמא עד הערב *Kol
hanogea bahem bemotam yitma ad ha'arev*. These are the ones that if
you touch them, you are טמא *tamei*. So basically things like moles,
lizards,
snails, certain types of... one says even a frog. Those are the
things that are listed. So okay, that's all very interesting that they're
טמא *tamei*. What relevance does it have for שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*? Let's
see what the משנה *Mishnah* says. שמונה שרצים Shmoneh Sheratzim? האמורים בתורה
*Shemonah sheratzim ha'amurim baTorah*, those eight animals, הצדן והחובל בהן ve'hachovel bahen
חייב chayav *hatzadan vehachovel bahen chayav*. If you capture them or you
wound them, you're חייב chayav *chayav*. Now okay, obviously why should you
not be? But you will remember yesterday, right, thank you, you'll remember
yesterday the position that the only thing you're חייב chayav *chayav* for
are things that are normally captured.
Now that means, you know, I'll give you just an important parallel
to that.
If I squeeze a fruit for their juices, okay,
there's an opinion that the only thing that is biblical, I think
we פוסקן *pasken*, that the only thing that is biblical is if
I squeeze grapes or olives, because anything else is not considered normally
squeezed for its juices. You know, lemons, apples, oranges, now for us
those are things that are very commonly squeezed, but the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* even talked about pomegranates, okay, so you have to use something
that's like maybe classically the thing that is squeezed for that. Now
there is a question by those, what about if reality changes? What
about if nowadays it's extremely common for people to squeeze lemon or
apples? Maybe not the apples you buy in the store, the oranges
you buy in the store, there you can distinguish different types of
species, but lemons, I mean, my god, what you use lemons for
is for squeezing them and getting out their juice. So would that
category change over time? And that's an important question, you know, by
that and by related הלכות *halachos*. So here too, you know, the
question could be, I mean, is this like an idea of אין
דרכו *ein darko*, like doing something with your left hand, like you
know, like a type of an issue of... of כלאחר יד *ke'le'achar
yad*? It seems different than that. It actually seems like it's like,
you know, some הלכות *halachos* are this applies only to things that
grow from the ground, this applies only to food. So in principle
this applies to the objects that are classically squeezed, or objects that
are classically captured. That was an issue you were introduced to yesterday
במינו ניצוד bimino nitzod. *bimino nitzod*. It doesn't seem like it's unanimous,
but there is that opinion out there, okay, that it has to
be במינו ניצוד bimino nitzod *bimino nitzod*. So this is saying, so
if we assume that, then these would be במינו ניצוד bimino nitzod,
*bimino nitzod*. Because people would capture them for at least תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* says maybe to use their skin. It's not exactly clear for
what purpose, but the assumption is that these would be normally captured.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says חייב chayav מפני שבמינו ניצוד *chayav mipnei shebimino
nitzod*. Okay, so you're חייב chayav *chayav* for capturing them. Number one,
we have to assume if we require a classic thing that is
captured that they are in that category. And if you make a
wound in them, you're חייב chayav *chayav*. Why not? You made a
wound, you took out blood. So let's contrast it to the next
list. ושאר שקצים ורמשים *Ushear shekatzim uremashim*, the other ones, החובל בהן
פטור patur *hachovel bahen patur*. If you make a wound you're exempt.
I'll get to them in a minute, let's first finish off talking
about capturing. הצדן *hatzadan*, if you capture them, לצורך *letzorech*, if you
do it for
a purpose that you want to, I don't know, somehow use the
animals in some way, חייב chayav *chayav*. You know, then... yeah, quiet,
I will get to that. שלא לצורך *shelo letzorech*, פטור patur *patur*.
If you are doing it for some, you know, not to capture
them, but you're doing it for some other purpose, again, so they're
not running around the house, so they're not going to bite you,
like we said before, then you're exempt. Okay, so why you're exempt
when you're doing it שלא לצורך *shelo letzorech*, we understand. That's a
type of a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melacha she'eina tzreichah legufah* like
we said before. So why are you חייב chayav *chayav* when it
is לצורך *letzorech*? So, okay, because it's צידה *tzidah*. Michael asks, okay,
so does that mean it's במינו ניצוד *bimino nitzod*? So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* actually says these are the category of שלא במינו ניצוד *shelo
bimino nitzod*. Other types of sort of rodents that are not in
this list are not normally captured. Which is funny, why should being
on the list make them, but okay, that's what רש"י *Rashi* says,
they're not normally captured. But תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has a problem. תוספות
*Tosafot* says if they're not normally captured, then even when you capture
them לצורך *letzorech* you should be פטור patur? *patur*. Okay, so תוספות
*Tosafot* says no, we have to assume that either this משנה *Mishnah*
is assuming you don't need things that are in a classic list
of normally captured, or that everything is on that list. And either
way though, so what's the difference between the first and the second?
That even though everything is במינו ניצוד *bimino nitzod* or even if
you don't need במינו ניצוד *bimino nitzod*, the things... the שמונה שרצים
Shmoneh Sheratzim *shemonah sheratzim* mentioned in the תורה Torah *Torah*, it's more
common to capture them. The things that are later in the list,
it's... they're... there's other reasons people
would... it's not so common to capture them or there's other reasons,
maybe they would be more like a snake and it would bite
you, so there might be other reasons that people would put something
over them and therefore in the first... In the first case, if
you have סתם intent, you're not thinking, you just capture without anything
particular in your mind, that's, it's defined as doing it with צורך,
tzorech, whereas in the second category, since it's not either as common
to capture them for to keep them or there's other reasons a
person might be capturing them, it more you need active intent to
be doing it in order to capture them because if you do
without anything particular in your mind, then we might not say that
it's considered to be capturing them for their own sake. So anyway,
that's it's a little hard to understand anyway, A, why does it
really matter that it's on the list or that it's the שמונה
שרצים shmonah sheratzim or not the שמונה שרצים? shratzim, But again, רש"י
makes the distinction whether they're במינו ניצוד. תוספות says if it was
that big of a difference, your כוונה kavana wouldn't matter. So we
have to say right, so we have to say that it is
all במינו ניצוד or it doesn't matter, we're not ruling you need
במינו ניצוד, and nevertheless some things require active intent, other things we
say מן הסתם, min hastam, they're the natural things to capture and
therefore they don't require active intent. So that's the difference of the
first half and the second half about whether they're about what your
intent is. Now how about the other about capturing and whether you
need active intent or not? How about the difference about חובל? chovel?
Why is חובל chovel in the first case חייב chayav and חובל
chovel in the second case not חייב? chayav, So here basically the
גמרא Gemara is going to assume, and this will also explain a
little bit why you might capture more things in the first case,
that the שמונה שרצים shratzim mentioned in the תורה, Torah, at least
according to one opinion, a distinguishing feature of them is that they
are considered to have as that they have skin as opposed to
the flesh underneath. Like there's a difference like if you think about
us humans, there's really no difference between our skin layer and the
flesh underneath, it's all sort of soft and continuous and so on,
very different from like animals, right, that has like a hide, a
tough hard hide and then, you know, some flesh under. You're making
a face Jolly, why, you think humans too the skin is different?
It's for mammals is the skin and the hide very similar? It's
just thicker for many animals.
Okay. All right. But still at a certain point you really consider
it much more distinct. Okay, now humans actually are considered maybe by
humans it is considered to be a skin. Okay, anyway, the, so
that's an issue that the גמרא Gemara has because by humans actually
חבלה chavala also is חייב. chayav So anyway, so why does any
of that matter? Because the גמרא Gemara assumes like this, I'll tell
you the way תוספות says. You hit somebody and you know you
see a black and blue mark. What's a black and blue mark?
That's it's blood that's caught underneath. So the גמרא Gemara. assumes if
you have skin, actually I said imprecisely wrong because humans are do
have skin for this purpose, if you have skin then we say
okay, you did חבלה chavala because even though no blood came out
to the air, but if you see the black and blue mark,
it means that there's blood that was broken from the blood vessels
captured underneath the skin and therefore you're חייב chayav. for having caused
that blood to come out even though it didn't come out into
the air. That would be by anything that has skin. Things that
are considered not to have an outer layer of skin or are
considered to be like continuous flesh and not considered distinct skin, we
would say if you actually released the blood it would have come
straight out, there's no outer layer skin to capture it underneath. So
either you you're only חייב chayav when the blood actually comes out,
not when you bang and make a black and blue mark, and
then I don't know how we think that black and blue mark
gets made, maybe the argument is it doesn't even make black and
blue mark, but the point is only if it has skin can
we say that you're חייב chayav before the blood comes out because
the skin captures the blood underneath. That's the idea here of the
distinction. So it makes two assumptions. Assumption number one is the eight
things mentioned in the תורה Torah are the only eight rodent type
animals that have skin, others don't have skin, they just have flesh.
And number two that only things that have skin, if a black
and blue mark would indicate that the blood is caught underneath, other
things we would say only when the blood actually leaves the leaves.
Now because of this assumption of a difference of the whether they
have skin or not, that's how רש"י explains why the first eight
are things that are more naturally captured. You capture them because you
want their hide, you want their skin. But again, knowing what's on
this list and knowing the world of creepy crawly rodent animals or
whatever, it's hard to believe that these are the eight only these
eight have skin and the others don't and what really is the
difference between it or not, but anyway that is the assumption. So
again, the first eight are considered to have some type of a
hide or skin and therefore they are normally captured and therefore you're
חייב chayav. for צד tzad and the חבלה chavalah you're חייב chayav,
because the blood coagulates beneath the skin. The others do not normally
have hide so they're not captured as frequently, you need specific כוונה
kavana in order to be
חייב chayav. for capturing and if you are חובל chovel and the
blood does not yet leave the body, go out into the air,
you are פטור patur because it is not considered to have actually
been caught under the skin.
Okay. חיה ועוף שברשותו, Chaya v'Of shebireshuto, now let's say you have
a animal or a bird in your under your control, meaning you
know you've got your house, your you know your chickens or your
your house dog, so it's not really even though if it's so
it's not locked up, it's not really lacking being captured, it's domestic
and it's you know you don't have to capture it, so הצדן
פטור hatzadan patur if you capture it you're exempt, והחובל בהן חייב
chayav. if you make a חבלה chavalah. you're חייב chiyuv cause those
animals as opposed to the שרצים, shratzim anything of the higher order
here species is considered to have skin and therefore blood would be
considered caught underneath the skin and you're חייב chiyuv for
חבלה.
chavalah, Wait a minute, since פטור means פטור and אסור, assur, why
is he considered צדה tzada at all? Why is he פטור?
Okay, that's true, again, so it's true, why isn't this in שמואל'ס
Shmuel's list? Yeah, okay, I don't know. Good question. All right, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מכדי תני החובל בהן
חייב מכלל דאית להו עור. Michdi tani hachovel bahen chayav miklal d'it
lehu or. So here the גמרא Gemara immediately says what I told
you. Since it is saying that you're חייב, chayav it jumps to
חבלה, chavalah we've discussed צדה tzada enough. So if it says you're
חייב for חבלה chavalah, in the first eight, presumably that's because they
have leather, skin—skin is maybe the best translation—hide maybe. So מאן תנא,
man tanna, who is the תנא tanna that says that all the
eight שרצים shratzim have have have a hide? So אמר שמואל רבי
יוחנן בן נורי היא. amar Shmuel Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri hi. It's
רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. דתנן, detnan, we taught
in חולין Chullin about a question about טומאה. tumah רבי יוחנן בן
נורי אומר שמונה שרצים יש להם עורות. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer
shmonah shratzim yesh lahem orot. The eight שרצים shratzim in the תורה
Torah have a hide, and the relevance of this is is that
their hide is not מטמא metamei the same way their flesh is.
Only their flesh is מטמא, metamei, not their hide. So he says
these eight have a hide that is distinct from their flesh. So
the גמרא Gemara assumes so that is what would explain why they
have a different הלכה halacha for צדה tzada and חבלה, chavalah because
they have a hide and the other animals are not considered to
have a hide. רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב אפילו תימא רבנן.
Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar Rav afilu teima rabbanan. No, even the
רבנן rabbanan who argue there and say that the hide of these
eight שרצים sheratzim, is מטמא metamei just like the flesh and don't
distinguish between the hide and the flesh for טומאה tumah, purposes. עד
כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי יוחנן בן נורי. Ad kan lo
pligi rabbanan alei d'Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri.
They only argue on him אלא לענין טומאה, ela l'inyan tumah, when
it comes to טומאה, tumah דכתיב אלה הטמאים לכם, dichtiv eleh hatmei'im
lachem, לרבות עורותיהן כבשרן. l'rabot oroteihen k'visran. Right? After it says the
the
after it lists them, the last five, it says אלה הטמאים לכם
eleh hatmei'im lachem, בכל השרץ. These are טמא in all animals, which
means that that that at least the last five, that that they
say that these last ones, that that these last ones, האנקה והכח
והלטאה והחומט והתנשמת, ha'anakah v'hakoach v'haleta'ah v'hachomet v'hatinshemet,
that these last ones actually their hide is just like their skin.
So he says they don't really say that it is physiologically just
like their skin. They just say because there's a פסוק pasuk that
says אלה הטמאים eleh hatmei'im לכם, לרבות עורותיהן כבשרן, l'rabot oroteihen k'visran,
halachically for טומאה tumah their hide of the last five counts like
their skin because after the last five it says אלה הטמאים eleh
hatmei'im and that extra אלה הטמאים eleh hatme'im, is coming to be
more inclusive that even their hide is מטמא. metamei. אבל לענין שבת
אפילו רבנן מודו. Aval l'inyan Shabbos afilu rabbanan modu. But for שבת
Shabbos even the רבנן rabbanan would agree. So here's interesting, it's always
interesting I think when the גמרא Gemara distinguishes between הלכה halacha categories.
And it says yes, in טומאה tumah. the רבנן rabbanan say that
five of them, the last five, their hide counts like their flesh
and their hide causes טומאה. tumah But it's not because they actually
say that physiologically the hide is the same as the flesh. Physiologically
it's different and it would have implications for שבת. Shabbos They just
say for טומאה tumah. the תורה tells you a חידוש chiddush that
their hide causes טומאה. tumah, All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says ולענין שבת לא פליגי? U'l'inyan Shabbos lo pligi? You
mean to tell me by שבת Shabbos that they don't argue? That
it doesn't apply by שבת Shabbos as well? והתניא, V'hatanya, we taught
in the ברייתא, braita, הצד אחד משמונה שרצים האמורים בתורה, Hatzad echad
mishmonah shratzim ha'amurim baTorah, if somebody captures one of the eight שרצים
sheratzim in the תורה, החובל בהן חייב, hachovel bahen chayav, if you
do a חבלה chavalah you're חייב. דברי רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Divrei
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. That's what רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri says. It's only רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri who says if you do a חבלה chavalah on all eight
of them. וחכמים אומרים אין עור אלא למה שמנו חכמים. Vachachamim omrim
ein or ela lema shemanu chachamim. No,
the only things that have a hide presumably for שבת Shabbos הלכות,
because that's what we're talking about, is the things mentioned by the
רבנן rabbanan that their hide is like the flesh for טומאה, tumah.
that the hide causes טומאה. tumah, Now the גמרא Gemara says first
of all before we even analyze this that was not said correctly.
אדרבא, למה שמנו חכמים אינהן דאין להם עור, Adarabba, lema shemanu chachamim
inhen d'ein lahem or, meaning the רבנן rabbanan gave a list of
these of these rodents that their hide was like their flesh in
order to cause טומאה, tumah. that their hide was a source of
טומאה. tumah. So when the things that were on the list, you
understand, the list is the following animals, their hides causes טומאה. tumah.
So that list tells you that their hide is not like their
flesh. So when the רבנן rabbanan say back to רבי יוחנן בן
נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, no, no, no, the only things that
have a hide are the things on the רבנן'ס rabbanan's list. No,
no, no, the things on the רבנן'ס rabbanan's list are the things
that don't have a hide, that their hide causes טומאה. tumah So
the גמרא Gemara says okay ואמר אביי v'amar Abaye so here's how
we have tweaked, we sort of you know what's how to read
that הכי קאמר hachi ka'amar this is how to read it: אין
עור חלוק מן הבשר אלא למה שלא מנו חכמים. Ein or chaluk
min habasar ela lema shelo manu chachamim.
There's only a hide distinct from a flesh for the things the
רבנן rabbanan didn't list. Okay, so anyway though how we read it,
meaning we've add in the word didn't in the משנה.
Okay, how we read it. We read these eight animals, רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says if you do חבלה chavala
on them you're חייב on שבת, Shabbos and the response back was
no, the only things that have skin are the things not on
the on the list of the רבנן. rabbanan. Only a few of
them have skin, not all of them. So you see their debate
of שבת. Shabbos. applies to שבת, Shabbos. whether it's considered to have
a hide or not. So אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, one
minute, but but we're not done yet saying that that's the right
text of the משנה. הא למה שמנוהו חכמים קאמר. Ha lema shemanuhu
chachamim ka'amar.
You can't add in the word שלא מנו חכמים, shelo manu chachamim,
that is not on the Rabbis' list. It's clear that the text
says on the Rabbis' list. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so
the Rava says before you start asking from that, let's make sure
we understand what it's saying. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, here's what it's
saying. אין עור מטמא כבשר אלא למה שמנו חכמים. Ein or metamei
kevasar ella lema shemanuhu chachamim.
What they're saying is, only things on the Rabbis' list is the
fle- is the hide considered like the flesh. Okay. So they're actually
emphasizing what is considered to be not a hide. They say, no
no no, the only- only a couple animals don't have a hide.
Gemara says, that also can't be what- how- what they're saying. מכלל
דרבי יוחנן בן נורי הנהו נמי דלא מנו חכמים מטמאים. Michlal deRabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri hanahu nami delo manu chachamim metama'in. That sounds, meaning
again, just- it's- it's getting a little complicated here, but here's what
it is, yes. Rabbi Yochanan- okay, they debate by טומאה tumah whether-
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says by טומאה tumah all of these eight
animals, the hide is distinct from the flesh and doesn't have טומאה
tumah. in the hide. And the Rabbis say, no, five of them,
the last five mentioned in the תורה actually the hide- the hide
is like the flesh and causes טומאה. tumah The question is would
they say the hide is like the flesh for שבת Shabbos purposes
as well? Would they say it's physiologically distinct? So the first argument
was, no, it's a טומאה tumah debate, by שבת Shabbos everybody agrees
it's distinct. Okay. But now we have a ברייתא. braisa. The ברייתא
braisa says that רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says
for שבת Shabbos. these eight animals if you do חבלה chavala you're
חייב and the response back is, no, there's only a hide for
the thing on the Rabbis' list. So important point number one is,
it sounds like this issue of whether all these animals have a
hide or not is an issue for שבת Shabbos. as well, because
they're specifically discussing the שבת Shabbos case. That's the emphasis of the
question. But before we get to proving that point, you have to
make sure we understand the right text here, because the response back
to רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri was, no, the
only things that have- have a hide are the things on the
Rabbis' list. But the Rabbis' list were things that didn't have a
hide. The Rabbis' list were the following things, their hide causes טומאה
tumah, because the hide is like the flesh. That's what we're dealing
with. Okay. So רבא, Rava, אביי Abaye tried to add in the
word don't, רבא Rava switches it the other way, to say that-
that- what the Rabbis are saying is that the only things that
don't have a hide are the things on the Rabbis' list. But
the problem is, is that sounds like מכלל דרבי יוחנן בן נורי
הנהו נמי דלא מנו חכמים מטמאים. michlal deRabbi Yochanan ben Nuri hanahu
nami delo manu chachamim metama'in. It sounds like Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
saying everything has- doesn't have a hide. And the response back is,
no, the only things that don't are the things on the Rabbis'
list. But that's not true, והקתני רבי יוחנן בן נורי אומר שמונה
שרצים יש להם עורות ולא מטמאין. ve-hakatani Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer
shemona sheratzim yesh lahem orot velo metama'in. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says
eight things have a hide, so the only reasonable response here is,
meaning Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says these eight things have a hide,
we know what the right way to respond to that is. Response
to that is, no, not all eight have a hide, only five
of them have a
hide, okay, or only three of them have a hide. The problem
is that that's not what the text of the ברייתא braisa said.
Okay. So אמר רב אדא בר מתנא תריץ הכי. Amar Rav Adda
bar Matna teretz hachi. Here's how you have to read it. וחכמים
אומרים לעניין טומאה אינו אלא למה שמנו חכמים. Vachachamim omrim le'inyan tumah
einu ella lema shemanuhu chachamim. And so it says look, you're right,
that when it- that- that by שבת Shabbat. you're right. Those eight
all have a hide, גזונטהייט. gezundheit. But when it comes to טומאה,
tumah, the only things that don't have- that don't have a hide
are the things that are on the Rabbis' list. So meaning for-
so it is a little complicated here, but the basic point is
is that there- Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says these eight things if
you do חבלה chavala you're חייב. There was a response back that
seemed to argue even by שבת. Shabbat. And what we're doing is
we're bracketing that response and saying they're not arguing back for שבת.
Shabbos They're saying for שבת Shabbos. you might be right. They're all
considered to have a hide. But for טומאה, tumah. the only- the
only a couple things are considered- you know, there's a list of
things that don't have a hide and only a couple things are
considered to have a hide for טומאה. tumah For שבת Shabbos. you
might be right.
Which was the same thing we always knew all- all along. טומאה
tumah is always very different.
Yeah, but anyway, the problem is that the simple sense of this
ברייתא braisa is they're arguing by שבת. Shabbos, But the text of
the ברייתא braisa doesn't work, so that gives us the opportunity to
change the text so that it's only talking about- that they're not
arguing about שבת. Shabbos Okay. So let's keep on going.
Okay, ואכתי ve'achati Gemara says לעניין שבת לא פליגי. le'inyan Shabbos lo
peligi. It's easier now. You still mean to tell me that by
שבת Shabbos they don't argue? והתניא אידך בברייתא, Vehatania idach bevraisa, הצד
אחד משמונה שרצים האמורים בתורה החובל בהן חייב בשרצים שיש להם עורות.
hatzad echad mishmona sheratzim ha'amurim baTorah hachovel bahen chayav basheratzim sheyesh lahem
orot. That if- if you capture the eight- these eight things, if
you make a חבלה chabalah. in the eight שרצים, you're חייב,
by the שרצים that have a hide. ואיזו היא חבורה שאינה חוזרת,
Ve'eizo hi chavura she'eina chozeret, and what is an example of a
wound that does not heal? נצרר הדם אף על פי שלא יצא.
Nitzrar hadam af al pi shelo yatza. If the blood coagulates under
the skin, like you get a black and blue mark, even though
it didn't go out. Okay, but anyway, it says not all of
the eight, only the eight that have- that have a hide.
A black and blue mark will heal.
Yeah, but I know, so if I have a minute I'll get
back to that. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says no, all eight have
a hide. So here it's very clear. We're arguing about שבת. Shabbat
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says all eight have a hide and all
eight is considered חבלה. chabalah And the first opinion says only of
those eight, only among those that do have a hide. So you
see within the eight there's a debate whether they all have a
hide or not. So it's very clear they argue by שבת. Shabbat,
So אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, so says Rav Ashi: מאן
תנא קמא man tana kama רבי יהודה דאזיל בתר גישא. Rabbi Yehuda
de'azal batar gisha. You're right. There's an opinion of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that says that there's a difference in the world of טומאה
tumah for a physiological difference. Not because of a פסוק pasuk of
אלה הטמאים, but actually says that some of them have גישא gisha
like a thickness to their skin and there's actually a physiological difference.
דתנן, we taught in the משנה, רבי יהודה אומר הלטאה כחולדה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer halta'a kichulda. So not everything, right, the חכמים hachamim that
base it on the פסוק pasuk say that everything mentioned here in
the second
פסוק, pasuk, האנקה והכח והלטאה והחומט והתנשמת, ha'anaka ve'hako'ach vehalta'a vehachomet vehatinshemet,
none of those are considered, all of none of those are considered
to have a hide. He says no, one of them, the הלטאה,
halta'a, which whatever it is, the lizard, is like
a כחולדה, kichulda, not a cat, whatever, a weasel.
So what does this mean? I know this is very complicated. What
it means is that Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says all eight of
them have a hide. Rabbis say the five listed at the end
for טומאה tumah. purposes, their hide is like their flesh, essentially don't
have a hide. But that's based on a פסוק. pasuk. Since it's
based on a פסוק, pasuk, what we're saying is physiologically they would
admit they all have a hide, but because of the פסוק, pasuk,
they're considered that in some of the cases the hide causes טומאה.
tumah Okay, so that's why we could say by שבת Shabbat. they
agree. Now there's a third opinion, which is that of רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying it's not based on
a פסוק, pasuk, it's based on physiology. And because it's based on
physiology, some of those in the last פסוק, pasuk, the hide is
like the flesh, but the הלטאה, halta'a, the lizard, the hide is
distinct from the flesh because it actually has a thickness to it.
So because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does not go based on a
פסוק, pasuk, he goes based on the physiology, he can apply his
distinction for טומאה tumah, also to
שבת. Shabbat. אבל רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי יוחנן לענין טומאה, aval rabbanan
de'pligi alei de'Rabbi Yochanan le'inyan tumah, but the rabbis who argue with
him by טומאה, tumah they're not basing themselves on physiology, they're just
based on a פסוק. pasuk. So therefore it's just a טומאה tumah,
point. לענין שבת מודה ליה, le'inyan Shabbos modei lei, they would agree
to him when it came to שבת. Shabbos So the גמרא Gemara
says: אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's true, האי דרבי יוחנן בן
נורי, hai de'Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, when Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri argues
and says all eight have a hide, it shouldn't just be Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri. It should be: דברי רבי יוחנן בן נורי ומחלוקתו
מיבעי ליה. divrei Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri u'machlokto mi'ba'ei lei. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri and the people he normally argues with, because he only
argues with them for טומאה, tumah. but when it comes to שבת,
Shabbos. they should all agree. So the גמרא Gemara says: you're right.
תני דברי רבי יוחנן בן נורי ומחלוקתו. tani divrei Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri u'machlokto. You fine, add to it that Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
and those that argue with him. So again, it was a little
bit complicated because, of course, you know, to know which of the
eight animals we're talking about and is it really true about the
eight and what's going on with טומאה. tumah But it basically boils
down to this: okay, there's an assumption that the eight, at least
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri makes the assumption that the eight mentioned in
the תורה have a hide. And therefore you more classically capture them
and if you do חבלה chabalah you're חייב. Now, by טומאה tumah.
he also therefore says the hide does not cause טומאה. tumah. There
are two arguments on him. One is the rabbis who argue and
say we got a פסוק pasuk that some of them does cause
טומאה. tumah That one we're saying: if it's all based on a
פסוק, pasuk, then you're not disagreeing with him in terms of the
physiological reality. And therefore, you might disagree with him by טומאה tumah.
because of the פסוק, pasuk, but physiologically you would agree that these
eight, their hides are distinct, and therefore by שבת you would agree.
And גמרא Gemara says: you're right, we will say that and in
the end we'll say that it's not only Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
that says that it's considered a חבלה by these eight, but even
those that argue with him by טומאה. tumah, That's however because it's
only based on a פסוק. pasuk. However, there's another person who argues
with him by טומאה, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, not based on a
פסוק. pasuk. Because he says even the פסוקים psukim don't break up
along those lines. The הלטאה halta'a is in another category. But he
says the argument is the difference is the physiological reality. Some of
these have the thick skin, have a hide, and others do not.
So therefore, the גמרא Gemara says according to him, he makes it
about a physiological difference. So for him, there would also be a
שבת difference as well. Okay, and that's the basic פשט pshat of
that, although some of the back and forth was confusing. Let's continue
now as the גמרא Gemara says like this.
It says: בעי מיניה לוי מרבי. ba'ei minei Levi mi'Rabbi. Levi asked
from Rabbi. מניין לחבורה שאינה חוזרת? aminayin le'chaburah she'eina chozeret?
How do you know the idea of a חבורה chaburah that's something
that does not heal? דכתיב, de'chtiv, the פסוק pasuk says,
meaning how do you know that that's the definition of making a
חבורה, chaburah, something that doesn't go back? היהפוך כושי עורו, hayahaphoch kushi
oro, so this is a very non-PC פסוק pasuk we're going to
be quoting. Will a, can an Ethiopian change his skin? ונמר חברבורותיו,
venamer chabururotav, or a leopard his spots, right, like a leopard changing
his spots? Okay, so מאי חברבורותיו? mai chabururotav? What does it mean
his spots? אילימא דקאי ריקמי ריקמי? Eileima d'kai rikmay rikmay? If you
mean the way that he is has like, you know, spot, different
sort of swaths of colors, a leopard, so האי ונמר חברבורותיו? Hai
v'namer chaburburotav? It shouldn't say his חברבורותיו chaburburotav which is here from
the we're reading it as the word חבורה chabura a wound, נמר
גווניו מיבעי ליה. Namer gvanav miba'ei lei. It should have said his
colors. אלא ככושי Ella k'khushi it means like an Ethiopian. מה עור
דכושי אינה חוזרת? Ma oro d'khushi eina chozeret?
The same way the skin of an Ethiopian does not ever go
back—it's a funny word go back—but whatever, it doesn't change, it always
remains that color, אף חבורה אינה חוזרת. Af chabura eina chozeret.
So not א נמר, a namer, not a leopard, but רש״י Rashi
says they're reading נמר namer here as a verb because נמר namer
from the verb like להמיר l'hamir to change. So they're saying היהפוך
כושי עורו ונמר חברבורותיו? Hayahfoch kushi oro v'namer chaburburotav?
Can a person's wounds נמר namer change? So a wound will never
heal, won't change. Now, again, what does this mean? So Michael says,
what do you mean? You mean you make a black and blue
mark, the wound doesn't get better? So the answer is yes, it
does get better, but presumably the sense is—well, or the sense is
that once the blood came out, the blood at least doesn't—I mean
what actually happens to the blood after of a wound? Where does
it go eventually? Does it get reabsorbed into the bloodstream?
Presumably cells die, right, or something?
I don't know. Anyway, it is funny what the phrase אף חוזרת
af chozeret means because it gets to the question of why making
a wound is חייב. You know, I kept on focusing on the
blood coming out. That's תוספות'ס Tosafot's point. He says the חייב of
this idea is that blood came out. So did it come out
into the air of the world or did it come out and
get caught under the skin?
רש״י Rashi seems to at least one place hint to the idea
that maybe the חייב of this is actually that you've made a
permanent wound in somebody. But if that's true, you know, the obvious
question that Michael asks is, do you really mean that anytime you
make a wound it never really heals? You know, so it's hard
to imagine. So it's easier to say what it means is that
since you've made a wound, somehow the blood that came out is
lost, you know, and that blood—it's like you've done some actual some
actual real wounding inside that you can't see. You didn't just change
color, there was actually some actual damage that was created. That seems
to be the way the גמרא Gemara is reasoning it. Okay, let's
try to get a little bit further here
about the moving on from these שמונה שרצים which is as I
said was a little complicated. Okay, ושאר שרצים, v'shaar sheratzim, the other
types of rodents that it's only if you have כוונה kavanah to
specific כוונה kavanah to capture them for a use.
So and—but if you wound them you're exempt presumably because unless the
blood actually comes out, it's not considered like you've actually sort of,
you know, released blood underneath the skin. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, wounding them you're exempt, ההורגן חייב hahorgan chayav if you kill
them you're liable.
מאן תנא? Man tanna? Who is the תנא tanna that says this?
Well, why shouldn't you be liable? That's clearly like, you know, killing
is a מלאכה. So אמר רבי ירמיה רבי אליעזר היא, Amar Rabbi
Yirmiah Rabbi Eliezer hi, it is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דתניא d'tanya
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר omer ההורג כינה בשבת כהורג גמל בשבת.
hahoreg kinah b'Shabbat k'horeg gamal b'Shabbat. If you kill a louse on
שבת it's like killing a camel on שבת, meaning that and he
is assuming that other the other Rabbis would argue and they would
maybe say small animals isn't in the category of killing, maybe only
if you kill, I don't know, a mammal or something. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, it's not about
it being small, so מתקיף לה רב יוסף, matkif lah Rav Yosef,
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said one minute, they're not debating other
like small animals. עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר אלא
בכינה, Ad kan lo pligi Rabbanan aleih d'Rabbi Eliezer ella b'kinah, they're
only debating a louse שאינה פרה ורבה she'eina parah v'rabah that it
does not it's not it does not procreate, meaning they believe that
presumably lice were spontaneous generation. So that's why they debate—it's not because
it's small. אבל שאר שרצים רבנן מודו Aval shaar sheratzim Rabbanan modu
but all other types of creepy crawly and rodent things דפרי ורבי
d'pari v'rabi that they do procreate, לא פליגי lo pligi everybody would
agree that you can't kill them. So it's only a very limited
debate about a louse which is understood to be spontaneous generation.
Is lice not a mammal?
Yeah, it's not considered—well we'll see in a minute. Why? Yeah, well
we'll take a look, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says. ושניהם
לא למדוה אלא מאילים V'shneihem lo lamduah ella m'eilim and they both
learned it from the rams because you know the גמרא Gemara spoke
about using the hides of rams for the משכן. Mishkan. So obviously
you had to kill the rams, so that was your paradigm for
what type of a killing is prohibited on שבת. רבי אליעזר סבר
כאילים Rabbi Eliezer savar k'eilim Rabbi Eliezer holds like rams, מה אילים
שיש בהן נטילת נשמה ma eilim sheyesh bahen netilat neshamah anything that
means taking a life, אף כל שיש בו נטילת נשמה af kol
sheyesh bo netilat neshamah anything taking a life, even the life of
a louse.
ורבנן סברי כאילים V'Rabbanan savri k'eilim and the Rabbis say like rams,
מה אילים דפרי ורבי ma eilim d'pari v'rabi no, it's not enough
that it's a life. They don't debate that it's a life, but
only certain types of lives, only lives that actually procreate.
אף כל דפרי ורבי Af kol d'pari v'rabi only things that procreate,
but certain types of things even if we would call them living
for other purposes, it's not the same maybe fullness of life or
whatever, it doesn't fit this paradigm and you're not liable for שבת.
So אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye אביי Abaye said to him,
this is all obviously with the mistaken... science that these things are
spontaneous generated.
Okay. אמר אביי וכינה אין פרה ורבה? Amar Abaye vekina ein parve
reba? So אביי Abaye actually challenges that. Since are you really telling
me a louse doesn't procreate? ואמר מר Ve'amar mar we taught יושב
הקדוש ברוך הוא וזן מקרני ראמים ועד ביצי כינים yoshev Hakadosh Baruch
Hu vezan mikarnei re'emim ve'ad beizei kinim that we say that God
sits up on his heavenly throne and he provides sustenance to all
creatures in the world, from the horns of the unicorns to the
to the eggs of lice. So actually, so God is you know
prov- so whatever, it's a beautiful metaphor, image. But the point is
we say eggs of lice. So you see lice lice have eggs,
so they do procreate.
What is the horns of the unicorn?
I have no idea. From the mightiest animals to the lowliest animals.
That's the point.
They suggest they're wild oxen.
Okay, I know, but the of- I question what a ראם re'em
is in Rabbinic. Alright. Okay. It's anyway,
right. So you see that they have eggs. So the גמרא Gemara
says no beautiful, but what does it say?
Let's just God
provides sustenance for all the creatures in the world. Right, המציא בכל
חי רצון hamatzi bechol chai ratzon exactly.
But for us we're focusing in on this ביצי כינים. beizei kinim.
They have eggs. So the of course you know when they check
for lice in the kids in the hair for school kids it's
for the it's for the eggs. Isn't it for the eggs that
the lice leave? Okay, anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you
see that they that they procreate. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
מינא הוא דמיקרי ביצי כינים. mina hu demikrei beizei kinim. No, no,
no, there's a species of animal called ביצי כינים. beizei kinim. It
doesn't mean the eggs of lice. It's a certain species. Okay. So
גמרא Gemara says והתניא vehatanya טפוי וביצי כינים. tfuyei ubeizei kinim.
So didn't we have another ברייתא Baraita that says right there? I
don't know exactly what the context is of this ברייתא, Baraita, but
okay, טפוי tfuyei which is some other type
of creepy-creature and ביצי כינים. beizei kinim. So the גמרא Gemara says
again, מינא הוא דמיקרי ביצי כינים. mina hu demikrei beizei kinim. Again,
it's some type of a species. Okay. Okay. So moving on. והרי
פרעוש. vaharei parosh.
What about a פרעוש? parosh? How do they translate פרעוש parosh there?
Flea.
Flea? Okay, some type of flea or or whatever, fly. Okay, פרעוש
דפרה ורבה parosh deparve raba that it procreates. ודתניא הצד פרעוש בשבת
רבי אליעזר מחייב ורבי יהושע פוטר. vedetanya hatzad parosh baShabbos Rabbi Eliezer
mechayev veRabbi Yehoshua poter.
This is debate about capturing a flea. Now we're assuming somehow capturing
is the same as killing, which is funny. So the גמרא Gemara
so don't you see that there's a general debate about small animals
whether it's a problem or not? So again the גמרא says it's
not about being small. אמר רב אשי צידה אריקה קרמית. Amar Rav
Ashi tzeida ariika karamit. You're challenging an issue of killing from a
discussion about capture. עד כאן לא פליגי רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע ad
kan lo pligi Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Yehoshua the debate about capturing a
flea is אלא דמר סבר דבר שאין במינו ניצוד חייב ומר סבר
פטור. ela demar savar davar she'ein bemino nitzod chayav umar savar patur.
What like we started before. That are you חייב for capturing something
that is not normally captured? Most people don't have a need for
a flea. So even if you captured it and you wanted to
make a flea farm or something like that, okay, you would still
be פטור according to one of them because it's not normally captured
and the other says I don't need something that normally is captured
as long as you're intending to capture it that's enough. So that's
the debate about the flea, but it's not because it's small. It's
a general question about capturing things that are not normally captured. אבל
הריגה aval hariga if it comes to killing, אפילו רבי יהושע מודה
afilu Rabbi Yehoshua modeh even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would agree. So
don't come telling me like all creatures large and small, like Horton
hears a Who, you know? It doesn't matter what's the line at
the end about something about it doesn't matter how small it is.
Anyway, it's not about it's small, it could be very tiny and
it's still a problem on שבת of killing. Yes? The whole issue
was very specifically about the flea, about the excuse me the louse,
because of an understanding that the louse did not procreate. Okay, so
we will continue with this tomorrow on שבת.